Guide to the Charles E. Taylor and Charles W. MacKey Papers, 1798-1896 DAR.1937.14
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Charles E. Taylor and Charles W. MacKey Papers
1798-1896
ULS Archives & Special Collections
MacKey, Charles W.
Taylor, Charles E., Lawyer
DAR.1937.14
6.67 Linear Feet (16 boxes)
The Charles E. Taylor and Charles W. MacKey Papers include documents from their legal practice in Oil City, Venango County, Pennsylvania, from 1850 to 1880. Their professional papers contain materials from clients in the oil, mining and railroad industries throughout Pennsylvania, Ohio, New York and West Virginia, as well as documentation of their business finances. The papers also include a small number of personal correspondence, receipts, and bills.
Biography
Charles E. Taylor and Charles W. MacKey were nineteenth century attorneys in Oil City, Pennsylvania. Taylor was a president judge of the Court of Common Pleas of Venango County. Their Venango County practice served private and corporate clients throughout the region, from New York to Ohio. During the 1860s, Taylor, Gilfillan & MacKey served a broad clientele of railroad, mining and oil companies. From the 1870s through the turn of the nineteenth century, Taylor and MacKey continued to represent these and other clients in civil and criminal cases.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection includes papers created in the legal offices of Taylor, Gilfillan & MacKey. The collection also includes Taylor's papers from his time as president Judge of the Court of Common Pleas of Venango County. Professional papers include legal documents related to cases and correspondence from the clients and business contacts. A significant collection of papers relate to the Allegheny Valley Railroad Company. Personal papers include receipts and bills for household goods, and personal correspondence from family, friends, and community members.
These materials are not in original order and were arranged by an unknown processor before they came to the Archives Service Center for description in 2007. Due to their preexisting arrangement, papers related to a single person or company may be found in multiple series within the collection. Professional correspondence are separated from other legal papers; within these series, some correspondence is alphabetized, and some are arranged chronologically. See series and subseries level scope content notes for further explanation of the arrangement of materials.
Arrangement
Series I. Legal Documents, 1798-1893
Series II. Client and Business Papers, 1853-1896
Series III. Bills and Receipts, 1855-1879
Series IV. Personal Papers of Charles MacKey, 1855-1876
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift to the Darlington Memorial Library in 1937.
Previous Citation
Charles E. Taylor and Charles W. MacKey Papers, 1798-1896, DAR.1937.14, Darlington Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Custodial History
This collection was located in the Darlington Memorial Library in the University's Cathedral of Learning until 2007 when it was moved to the ULS Archives Service Center for processing, storage, preservation and service. However, it remains in the custodianship of the ULS Special Collections Department.
Legal files; Legal documents; Venango County (Pa.) -- History; Oil City (Pa.) -- History; Practice of law -- Pennsylvania -- Venango County -- History; Judges -- Pennsylvania -- Venango County; Lawyers -- Pennsylvania -- Oil City; Financial records; Receipts (Financial records); Personal correspondence; Legal correspondence; Pennsylvania. Court of Common Pleas (Venango County); Taylor, Gilfillan & MacKey; MacKey, Charles W.; Taylor, Charles E., Lawyer
- Legal Material, 1798-1893; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains the papers created by Taylor and MacKey in the legal offices of Taylor, Gilfillan & MacKey in the 1860s, and, later, Taylor & MacKey. These chronologically arranged "legal documents" include: drafts of real estate agreements, notes for cases (some of which identify the client), ledgers of client payments, attorney fee forms and checks, subpoenas, witness depositions, and ephemera. This series also contains limited correspondence that relates the Taylor & MacKey firm. The materials reflect the breadth of their practice, including their work for clients in their town of Oil City, Venango County. The firm also represented clients from Altoona, Meadville, Erie, Pittsburgh, and Cleveland, as well as towns in upstate New York. These papers refer to property loss cases, such as Ellis Harris vs. Imperial Fire Co. and estate and real estate cases heard in the Court of Common pleas of Venango County. Also present are drafts of land agreements presumably created by Taylor & MacKey. Many of the papers relate to clients in the oil, mining and railroad businesses, including the Tank Oil Company, the Atlantic Petroleum Company, the Pithole Creek Petroleum Company, the Osceola Oil Company, the Island Oil Company, the Fountain Oil Company, Ritchie Oil Company, and the Oil Well Supply Company. The firm also practiced criminal law, including two murder cases in 1863, and cases argued before the Orphan's Court. The majority of these papers are arranged chronologically. However, depositions and court transcripts from cases of note are located in Box 8, including a worksite bludgeoning murder between log rollers, an 1863 stabbing death, two undated shooting deaths, and the trial of a man accused of raping an eleven-year-old neighbor in the woods near her home.
  - Legal Documnents, 1798-1893; 1.
    This subseries is chronologically arranged "legal documents" include: drafts of real estate agreements, notes for cases (some of which identify the client), ledgers of client payments, attorney fee forms and checks, subpoenas, witness depositions, and ephemera. The materials also include limited amount of correspondence that relate to the Taylor & MacKey firm. The materials reflect the breadth of their practice, including their work for clients in their town of Oil City, Venango County.
    - Legal documents, 1798-1860 (Box 1, Folder 1-10)
    - Legal documents, 1861-1864 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
    - Legal documents, 1864-1866 (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
    - Legal documents, 1867-1873 (Box 4, Folder 1-9)
    - Legal documents, 1874-1893 (Box 5, Folder 1-10)
    - Legal documents, undated (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
    - Legal documents, undated (Box 7, Folder 01-04)
    - Case notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Case notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Notes and Judgements, 1860-1875; 2.
    The notes and judgements subseries included case notes on shooting, murder testimony, and other general legal documentation.
    - Notes and Judgements, general, 1860-1875 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Bludgeoning murder testimony, 1863 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Stabbing murder case notes, 1863 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Oil contract draft, 1870 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Testimony of breach of contract, 1871 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Shooting Case Notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Shooting Case, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Account of fire losses, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Murder case testimony, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Rape case, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Client and Business Papers, 1853-1896; II.
  This series contains correspondence from the clients and business contacts of Taylor & MacKey. The correspondence, receipts, and ledgers in this series are split into two subseries; the first is arranged alphabetically, and the second chronologically. These materials reflect Taylor & MacKey's work for mining and oil interests, such as the Iron City Oil Works of Pittsburgh, the Standard Lubricating Oil Works of Parkersburg, West Virginia, the Walnut Hill Coal Company, and private clients. Their communications with other attorneys, such as C. S. Poor, of Shamburgh, Pennsylvania demonstrate their broader involvement in the legal field. Related to their work, a map of "Oil Creek Lands" dated 1860 depicts numbered plots owned by Hussey, McBride, Haldeman and Farmer along Oil Creek in Cherrytree and Cornplanter Townships, Venango County, Pennsylvania. An additional, though undated, map shows the Island Well on Ball Farm near Pithole Creek and its confluence with an unnamed tributary. Client papers of the the Allegheny Valley Railroad Company include suits filed against the company for damage and injury caused by accidents. Many of the client papers relate to civilian property damage claims.
  - Client and Business Papers, Alphabetical Arrangment, 1856-1896; 1.
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by the last name of the author, or sometimes by the name of the company. Some folders represent a single author or company, while others are labeled simply with a letter and contain correspondence from multiple authors. Some clients in the oil industry have been alphabetized seperately in Box 12.
    - A, 1858-1876 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Allegheny Valley Railroad Company, 1860-1893 (Box 9, Folder 02-12)
    - Henry Allebach, 1958-1961 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Atlantic and Great Western Railroad, 1869-1879 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - A. G. Curtin, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - B, 1859-1877 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - C, 1859-1871 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Chauncey M. Depew, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - D, 1858-1874 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - E, 1863-1864 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - F, 1860-1875 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - G, 1858-1871 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - H, 1858-1876 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Harris (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - I, 1864-1873 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - J, 1858-1896 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Jackson Oil Company, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - S. P. Johnson, 1858-1871 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - K, 1856-1871 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - L, 1863-1875 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Lake Shore and Michigan Southern Railway Company, 1869-1874 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Laytonia Town and Oil Company, 1867 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - M, 1858-1882 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - M, 1858-1882 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Mountain Oil Company, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - N, 1864-1871 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - New York Pennsyvania and Ohio Railroad, 1885 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - O, 1869-1874 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Oil City and Pithole Railroad, 1869-1872 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - P, 1869-1876 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad, 1870 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Pennsylvania Reserves, 1876 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - C. S. Poor, 1870-1871 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Q, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - R, 1858-1871 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - N. B. Robinson v Oil City Gas Company, 1879 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - S, 1867-1875 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - S, 1867-1875 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - T, 1870-1871 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - C. E. Taylor, 1864-1874 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Isaac Taylor, 1873 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Taylor MacKey, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Titusville and Tidiote Railroad, 1821-1871 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - U, 1874 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Simon Ulman, 1860 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Vincent, 1869 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - V, 1863 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - W, 1859-1879 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Wilson, 1869-1871 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Y-Z, 1871-1879 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Oil-related clients A-E, 1860-1871 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Oil-related clients F-L, 1860-1871 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Oil-related clients M-R, 1864-1879 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Oil-related clients S-Z, 1865-1887 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Map of Island Well on Ball Farm, undated (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Map of Oil Creek Lands, 1860 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Ledgers of client accounts, undated (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Client and Business Papers, Chronological Arrangment, 1853-1875; 2.
    Correspondence in this subseries is arranged chronologically by year. There is overlap between these materials and alphabetized correspondence in the previous subseries.
    - 1853-1870 (Box 13, Folder 01-13)
    - 1870-1875 (Box 14, Folder 01-08)
- Bill and Reciepts, 1855-1879; III.
  This series includes reciepts and bills for purchases made by Charles MacKey. Most of these materials document the purchase of items for personal use, including various dried goods, coal, food, liquor, newspaper and legal journal subscriptions, milled grains, and ammunition. The only business-related purchases are for stationary and other paper goods, and tax reciepts are also present.
  - A, 1870-1872 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - B, 1855-1872 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Cooper, 1864-1871 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - C-D, 1860-1876 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - E-G, 1860-1872 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - H, 1869-1876 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Johnson, Brough & Bostwick, 1870-1875 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - K-L, 1868-1873 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - M, 1872-1887 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - N-P, 1860-1873 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - R, 1864-1873 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - S, 1861-1871 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - T-V, 1871-1874 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - W, 1871-1879 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Bank reciepts, 1868-1872 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous reciepts, undated (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Tax receipts, 1871 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Credit A-L, 1862-1874 (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Credit M-Z, 1861-1874 (Box 15, Folder 19)
- Personal Papers of Charles MacKey, 1855-1876; IV.
  The series includes personal correspondence, an insurance policy, and papers related to local politics. Because the personal letters are written to Charles or Charlie, and no envelopes are present, it is presently unclear if these materials belong to Taylor or Mackey. Much of the personal correspondence is from Thomas and Catherine Kane of Philadelphia. Both MacKey and Taylor received letters from Masons in Pennsylvania, and each are addressed as "brother." Masonic materials include a form letter notifying Taylor about train reservations made for him on the Pennsylvania Railroad, a letter regarding a three-sided brass lamp MacKey had ordered, and an announcement for a meeting at the Myrtle Lodge. A letter frrom Charles M.S. Powell of the Knights Templar, Pennsylvania, can also be found among the Masonic correspondence. Additional personal correspondence are alphabatized by the last name of the author; within the alphabatized correspondence, there is a letter from G.A. Allen regarding Taylor's son, Johnny, who was taken out of school and employed at a tannery.
  In addition to correspondence, this series contains materials relating to local politics, including the contested election of R. D. McCready to the general assembly, and materials relating to a board of elections inquiry into Democrats buying votes with whiskey. It is unclear whether these materials relate to Taylor or MacKey's professional or civic lives.
  - Correspondence, local politics, 1868-1876 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Petition contesting election of John P. Park, 1875 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - List of voters in Venango County, 1874 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Charles Taylor Insurance policy, 1880 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence from Thomas and Catherine Kane, 1855-1857 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Masonic correspondence to Taylor MacKey, 1859-1871 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Personal correspondence A-D, 1858-1876 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Personal correspondence E-L, 1859-1874 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Personal correspondence M, 1864-1876 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Personal correspondence N-Z, 1862-1882 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Personal correspondence, undated (Box 16, Folder 11)